[Music]
Herbal Life is a multi-billion dollar
multi-level marketing supplement company
that was forced to pay hundreds of
millions of dollars to settle charges of
deception and corrupt business practices
it also holds the distinction of being
the dietary supplement most frequently
implicated in injuring the livers of
consumers herbal does not mean innocuous
cases of severe liver toxicity
associated with Herbal Life supplements
started to be published in 2007 around
the world as the accompanying editorial
summarize there were 22 cases of liver
damage following Herbal Life intake in
the first two reports with two patients
developing fulminant liver failure
requiring liver
transplantation only one
survived the editorial concluded that
this clearly shifts the risk benefit
ratio against its use maybe it's
contaminated with chemicals or heavy
metals maybe due to contamination with a
liver toxic bacteria found in implicated
products additional reports continued to
be published followed by rebuttal
written by Herbal Life company
Representatives questioning cause and
effect no small task given that people
were taking up to 17 different Herbal
Life Products at one time so how strong
is the evidence
a key factor to look for is rechallenge
tests or positive
reexposure did someone decide to take
the product again after the initial
liver injury result and did their
symptoms return on rechallenge based on
stringent causality assessment methods
like positive reexposure tests cause and
effect is considered probable for at
least a few Herbal Life Products there's
such a moving Target though with
hundreds of different products marketed
globally in over 88 markets where in
many cases the formula is unique to a
region positive rechallenge cases
continue to be published confirming the
toxic cause of liver damage from Herbal
Life Products perhaps by triggering an
autoimmune reaction this fatal case of a
24-year-old woman was attributed to
Herbal Life Products which were
evidently found to contain heavy metals
traces of a psychotropic recreational
agent and pathogenic bacteria the paper
was subsequently taken down for quote
unquote legal reasons after legal
threats by Herbal Life liver talks is a
federal initiative between the National
Institutes of Health and the National
Library of Medicine to categorize the
likelihood that substances can damage
the liver all the way up to the highest
likelihood category a meaning it's a
well-known well described and well
reported cause of liver damage and
that's exactly how it characterized
Herbal Life supplements a
well-established cause of clinically
apparent liver injury
[Music]